Guide to the Pat LittleDog Papers
The Wittliff Collections
Pat LittleDog Papers
1954-1984
The Wittliff Collections
LittleDog, Pat, 1941-
SWWC.050
1.5 Linear Feet
3 boxes
The Pat LittleDog Papers are comprised of diaries, typescripts, correspondence, artifacts, and published journals.
Scope and Contents
This collection is comprised of diaries, typescripts, correspondence, artifacts, and published journals. The bulk of the collection is formed by the typescripts of How It Happened That I Came to Live in the West. The Correspondence series also relates to this novel. Diaries date from LittleDog's teenage years in Germany, a red Hofner accordion belonged to LittleDog's father. Dates range from 1954-1984. Books and periodicals cataloged separately.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research
Source of Acquisition
Donated by Pat LittleDog since 1992
Biographical Notes
Novelist, short-story writer, and journalist Pat Ellis Taylor was born June 23, 1941 in Bryan, Texas. She lived in Weisbaden, Germany during her teenage years in the mid to late 1950s. She received her B.A. in 1969 and her M.A. in 1976, both from the University of Texas at El Paso. Her first novel, Border Healing Woman, won a Southwest Book Award in 1981, and her third, Afoot in a Field of Men and Other Stories from Dallas' East Side, won a Texas Circuit Book Award. In 1991, Taylor changed her named to Pat LittleDog and published In Search of the Holy Mother of Jobs.
Women authors, American -- Texas -- 20th century; Diaries; LittleDog, Pat, 1941-
- Diaries, 1954-1958
  Series Description
  This series contains diaries that date from LittleDog's teenage years in Germany.
  - 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Works, 1977-1984
  The bulk of this series is formed by the typescripts of How It Happened That I Came to Live in the West.
  - "When the War-Father Appears" typescript, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Afoot in a Field of Men" mock-up layout (Box 2)
  - "How I Came to Live in the West", circa 1977-1980
    - Typescript (57 pages) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Typescript (Chapter 1) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Typescript fragments (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - As published by chapters in The Southwestern Art Form (photocopies) (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence
  The bulk of the correspondence in this series relates to the novel How It Happened That I Came to Live in the West.
  - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Artifacts, undated
  This series contains three items: corded belt, Jose Cuervo yellow bandana, and Red Hofner accordion owned by LittleDog's father.
  - Corded belt, Jose Cuervo yellow bandana (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Red Hofner accordion owned by LittleDog's father; photograph of him with accordion (Box 3)
- Associated Journals, circa 1970-1989
  This series contains journals that LittleDog edited or was otherwise associated with.
  - Hot Springs Information Network (LittleDog, Editor); Hot Springs Gazette Bathside Guide to Foreign Planets, Issue No. 6, 1979, 1981, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Assorted issues of small press journals LittleDog has been associated with, circa 1970-1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)